Guide to the George Vernadsky Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Vernadsky papers
1929-1969
MS 520
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
(18 boxes)
The papers consist of manuscript drafts of George Vernadsky's published books and articles on Russian history. Also included in the papers are photostats of documents used by Vernadsky in his research and writing.
Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973
Related Materials
George Vernadsky Papers, Bakhmeteff Archive, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of George Vernadsky, Sergei Pushkarev, and Howard B. Gotlieb between 1957 and 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The George Vernadsky Papers consist of manuscripts and typescripts for several of Vernadsky's published books and articles on Russian history. The papers also include phostats of documents used by Vernadsky in his research and writings. The materials represent only a small portion of Vernadsky's papers, the bulk of which are in the Bakhmeteff Archives in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library of Columbia University.
The papers, which include manuscripts, in chronological order, followed by the articles, which are also in chronological order. Manuscripts for Vernadsky's The History of Russia, a major work which was revised and reissued in several editions, comprise the majority of the papers. Included with the manuscripts for this title are research materials in the form of photostats of ancient Greek texts. At the end of the papers there is a manuscript for an autobiography of Vernadsky's life from his birth until 1917.
Biographical / Historical
George Vernadsky was born in St. Petersburg, Russia, on August 20, 1887. He studied at Moscow University and received a Magister degree in Russian history from the University of St. Petersburg in 1917. He taught at universities in Russia and Czechoslovakia before emigrating to the United States and joining the Yale University faculty in 1927. He authored several volumes on the history of Russia. Vernadsky died on June 12, 1973 in New Haven, Connecticut.
History -- Study and teaching; Soviet Union -- History; Manuscripts (for publication); Historians; Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - A History of Russia, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
  - A History of Russia, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Photostats, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18-24)
  - Lenin: A Red Dictator, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 25-30)
  - A History of Russia
    - Volume 1: Ancient Russia, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 31-35)
    - Volume 1: Ancient Russia, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 36-41)
    - Volume 2: Kievan Russia, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 42-54)
  - The Origins of Russia: manuscript, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 55-64)
  - The Origins of Russia: manuscript, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 65-76)
  - The Origins of Russia: manuscript, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 77-79)
  - The Origins of Russia: typescript, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 80-89)
  - A History of Russia
    - Volume 4: Russia at the Dawn of the Modern Age, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 90-101)
    - Volume 4: Russia at the Dawn of the Modern Age, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 102-114)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 115-128)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 129-140)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 141-155)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 156-169)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 170-184)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 185-200)
    - Volume 5: Tsardom of Muscovy, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 201-211)
  - Articles
    - "Brotherhood 'Prijutino'" (English), Undated (Box 18, Folder 212)
    - "Brotherhood 'Prijutino'" (Russian), Undated (Box 18, Folder 213-216)
    - "Eurasian Nomads and their Impact on Medieval Europe", Undated (Box 18, Folder 217-221)
    - "Ossetian Tale of Dada Mstislav", Undated (Box 18, Folder 222-223)
    - "Toxar, Tima, T'mutorkani", 1956 (Box 18, Folder 224)
    - "Century of Russian Foreign Policy", 1961 (Box 18, Folder 225)
    - "Chronological Outline of My Life, 1887-1917" (Russian), 1969 (Box 18, Folder 226-227)